Henry Wadsworth Longfellow Dana, Scottsboro Boys trial collection, 1932-1938
Emory University
Scottsboro Boys trial collection, 1932-1938
Dana, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, 1881-1950.
Manuscript Collection No. 1033
.25 linear ft. (1 box)
Materials collected by Henry Wadsworth Longfellow Dana primarialy concerning the rape trials of the Scottsboro Boys, including correspondence, broadsides, and newspaper clippings.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 2005.
Restrictions on Access
Unrestricted access.
Biographical Note
Henry Wadsworth Longfellow Dana (1881-1950), grandson of the poet Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, was a teacher, lecturer, and writer. He received his A.B., A.M. and Ph.D. from Harvard University and taught there from 1908 to 1910. From 1912 to 1917 he taught at Columbia University until he was fired for his anti-war stance. Dana took an interest in leftist politics and the rights of workers.
The Scottsboro Boys were a group of nine African American men accused of the rape of two white women on the Southern Railroad freight run from Chattanooga to Memphis on March 25, 1931. Their first trial occurred in Scottsboro, Alabama.
Scope and Content Note
The collection primarily contains materials collected by Henry Wadsworth Longfellow Dana concerning the rape trials of the Scottsboro Boys from 1932-1940 including correspondence, broadsides, and newspaper clippings. The majority of the collection concerns activities that took place in Boston, Massachusetts. Much of the correspondence consists of mimeographed circular letters concerning the progress of the trial and pleas for financial support from the International Labor Defense National Office, the Boston Scottsboro Defense Committee, the National Committee for the Defense of Political Prisoners, the Neighborhood Scottsboro Defense Club, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, and the Scottsboro-Mooney Defense Conference. A few letters are personally addressed to Dana from David F. Jeffreys, Mary E. Moore, Secretary-Treasurer of the local Neighborhood Scottsboro Defense Club, Edmund J. O'Neal, principal of the Montgomery County Training School, and the International Labor Defense National Office. The remainder of the collection consists of a blank petition to Bibb Graves, governor of Alabama, newspaper clippings concerning the trials, an announcement of a play presented by the John Reed Club directed by Dana, and handbills announcing meetings and speeches in Boston, including an announcement of a meeting at which Dana spoke in 1932 and an appearance of Ruby Bates. Published pamphlets accompanying the collection have been cataloged.
Arrangement Note
Arranged by record type.
Selected Search Terms
Corporate Names
Scottsboro Defense Committee.
Topical Terms
African Americans--Civil rights.; Scottsboro Trial, Scottsboro, Ala., 1931.; Trials (Rape)--Alabama--Scottsboro.
Related Materials in Other Repositories
Henry Wadsworth Longfellow Dana papers, 1774-1992, Longfellow National Historic Site, Boston, Massachusetts.
Container List
- Article, Cunard, Nancy, "Scottsboro," Close Up, September 1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Announcement, A meeting to discuss the cases of Edith Berkman and the Scottsboro Boys, New England Committee for Defense of Political Prisoners, Boston, Massachusetts, June 16, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Announcement, "Scottsboro" play, John Reed Club, Boston, Massachusetts, April 7, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Boston Scottsboro Defense Committee, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, International Labor Defense National Office, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, David F. Jeffreys to HWL Dana, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Mary E. Moore to HWL Dana, 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, National Committee for the Defense of Political Prisoners, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, Neighborhood Scottsboro Defense Club, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, O'Neal, Edmund J., 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, Scottsboro-Mooney Defense Conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, West Indian American Subcommittee of the International Trade Union Committee of Negro Workers, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Handbill, "Scottsboro New Trial Emergency Fund, Scottsboro-Mooney Defense Committee," Boston, Massachusetts, March 5, [?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Handbill, "Victory Meeting, Welcome the Freed Scottsboro Boys, Boston, Massachusetts," November 23, [?] (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Handbill, "Mass Meeting, Heart the Truth from the Lips of Ruby Bates, Mrs. Janie Patterson, and Richard B. Moore," Boston, Massachusetts, May 27, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Leaflet, "5 Years in Hell," Scottsboro Defense Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- New Pioneer cover concerning the Scottsboro Boys, October 1932 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Newspaper clippings, 1931-1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Petition, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)